[For the arson case,]
明堂一事
you've already docked your pay,
你已自罚俸禄
guards got punished,
一应看守也已重罚
[and the dead guy]
自焚者已死
[has only an elder left in his family.]
家里只剩一孤老
So,
这事
the case is rested.
便罢了
[Since you just got married,]
你昨日刚刚大婚
you may skip briefings
这几日的早报
for a few days,
就免了
and spend some time with
在家里好好陪陪
your bride.
自己的新娘
Yeah.
是啊
I heard you stayed up
听闻大阁领
all night on the investigation,
连夜彻查明堂火案
[haven't gone home.]
一夜未归呢
[Chief Shen is truly devoted]
大阁领为太皇太后
to his duties.
尽忠职守
But the bride was alone on the wedding night.
只是可怜了新娘子
He should be granted
太皇太后是该给大阁领
[a few days' leave as a reward.]
好好放几日假
[Looks like his "devotion" might be]
怕是这尽忠职守是假
a front to ignore his bride.
故意冷遇新娘是真吧
[I'm their matchmaker.]
大阁领的婚事
[But when I checked]
是老臣牵的线
on the bride this morning,
今晨老臣前去探望
she was
发现这新娘子
gone.
竟被气跑了
[No one in]
这沈府上下
[the Shen Mansion]
都不知道
[knows where she went.]
这新娘子去往何处
Lady Yan can't just
莫不是这颜家娘子
vanish like that after
刚刚嫁进大阁领府
[the wedding, can she?]
就人间消失了吧
Chancellor Lai.
来中丞
[How dare you jest]
太皇太后近前
in front of Her Highness?
怎可戏言
Your Highness.
太皇太后
[I was]
来中丞
[just being concerned.]
也是为大阁领而忧心啊
I heard that
老臣听闻
Your Highness wanna
太皇太后要给内卫府
[boost IG's power,]
增加些职权
[which is a good thing.]
这本是好事
But if Chief Shen can't
可这大阁领
even manage his own family affairs,
内宅都打理不好
how's he gonna handle
如何能帮着太皇太后
more responsibility?
执掌重权呢
Shen.
沈爱卿
What do you say?
你怎么看
Prime Minister Zhang is right.
张相所言极是
I'll sort out
一屋不扫
my family business.
何以扫天下
I'm heading home
臣这就回去
to patch things
安抚妻子
up with my wife.
处理好内宅之事
I won't let you down.
定不负太皇太后所望
Why not wash up?
你又不是去
Like you
彻夜查案去了
were working overnight.
怎么又没梳洗就睡了
Chief Shen
难不成
didn't come into your bed chamber?
是大阁领真没入厢房
Is Yan Xing
这颜六娘
your niece?
是你的外甥女吧
Your Highness.
启禀太皇太后
She's the daughter
这颜六娘
of Madame Jin from the Yan family.
乃颜府金姨娘所出
And Jin
这金姨娘
is my sister.
正是在下的姐姐
Don't worry.
你放心吧
[Shen may seem]
沈渡这小子
[wild and unruly,]
看着桀骜
but he has his principles.
但其实是有章法的
[He wouldn't do anything]
他不会做出什么
truly outrageous.
真的出格的事
Agreed.
是
I'll go to the Liang's myself.
我亲自去一趟梁府
What, you?
那谁谁谁
What brings you here?
你来干什么
Chief Clerk Wu,
吴主事
I heard there's a case.
我听说这里面有案子
There is one.
案子是有
But it's none of your business.
跟你有关系吗
I heard you
我听说
got married to the
昨天你上了花轿
Shen Mansion yesterday,
说是嫁到了大阁领府
but why here
怎么今天
in your wedding dress?
穿着婚衣就出来了
Did they
怕不是
kick you out or something?
让人给赶出来了吧
You...
你
She's always
此女子办差啊
stirring up problems.
总是出幺蛾子
Miss Yan's sharp,
六娘心思机敏
and learned a lot from Chen Wen,
又曾师从典狱司监陈瘟
the warden of the prison.
得了他不少查案的真传
And she has
一直以来
helped us a lot with investigation.
帮了我们异良人不少忙
Right.
就是
Mr. Wu and Mr. Xu.
吴主事 徐帅
I apologize for my
是六娘一时心急
rudeness.
失礼了
I just wanna see if
我就是想来看看
there were
案发现场
any clues left.
还有没有什么线索
Leave cases to experts.
查案有专门的人手
As a clerk,
你一个书吏
just manage
管好卷宗即可
the records.
查什么案呢
Go back to the Ministry of Justice
去去去 先回刑部衙门
and change your clothes.
把衣服换了
Mr. Wu.
吴主事
Are you just back from the west?
你这是刚从西郊回来吧
[My Lord.]
大人
Look.
你看
The blue pattern on
吴主事这个衣袖上
his sleeve is so beautiful.
这个蓝色的花好漂亮啊
[You see?]
你看你看
It must be Mrs. Wu's
看来是夫人
new stitch.
又学会了新的绣样
Good to
年轻人
be curious,
好学上进
kid.
好事 好事
Go inside
想查案呢
and take a closer look.
就进去仔细瞧
But don't
但是不要影响
interfere with the investigation.
人家异良人办案
And
还有
stay out of it.
不该管的事少管
What's going on?
到底怎么回事啊
Mrs. Wu can't sew a stitch.
老吴的夫人哪里会绣样
Wu's lackey Feng Gui's
他那个狗腿子冯贵
been to the west a lot,
近日频繁来往西郊
legs all muddy.
腿上都是西郊泥点子
Wu was given a deed.
还给了他房契
It's most likely
十有八九啊
Wu has a mistress out there.
是在西郊养了外室
Mis...
外
Let's go.
走走走
I'm a clerk from the MJ,
我是刑部书吏
can I take a look?
可以去看看吗
If you're not afraid, go ahead.
不害怕便看吧
So,
师傅
did you spot anything
您之前发现过什么
weird earlier?
有不寻常的地方吗
No, nothing.
贫僧暂未发现
Heard they
听说他俩
were holding each other
刚被挖出来的时候
tight when dug up.
还紧紧抱在一起的
[Both]
这二人
[hearts gone,]
都是心脏被挖
[bled out.]
失血而死
[Woman's face scratched,]
女子面部被划
[but calm.]
但神态安详
[Man's body was intact,]
男子尸身完好
but his skin was dark.
皮肤发黑
[The scratches and blood indicated]
看划痕和血迹
[he was scratched after death.]
是死后才被划的
Despite the weather,
如此天气
[the bodies didn't]
尸体竟然没有
[smell putrid,]
散发腐臭之气
[but instead emitted]
甚至还散发着一股
a fragrance of mixed herbs.
药材混合的香味
Yan.
六娘
Are you serious?
你不会是魔怔了吧
Fragrance? How's that possible?
尸体哪还会有香味啊
[Yan.]
六娘
She's right on the mark.
六娘所说分毫不差
This morning,
今晨小沙弥
a young monk found the bodies
在寺外竹林
while digging for bamboo shoots
挖竹笋的时候
outside the temple.
挖到了尸体
We've identified the man
已经查明男子
as Liang Chenzhong, the eldest son
是原工部梁侍郎家
of Mr. Liang from the Ministry of Works,
嫡出的长子梁尘重
[and the woman as Kuang Zhanxin,]
女子是
[a musician from Pingkang music house.]
平康坊的乐人邝盏心
Love suicide,
这难不成
maybe?
是殉情
No.
不会
What poison
男子皮肤发黑
made his skin go dark?
可有查出是中了什么毒
-The poison... -[Zhong.]
他所中之毒 重儿
Zhong.
重儿
-My son! -Mrs. Liang.
我的儿啊 梁大夫人节哀
[My condolences.]
节哀节哀
[Zhong.]
重儿
That poison thing...
你们刚刚说的中毒
Your son was poisoned by
令郎身体所中之毒
a toxic plant named Guanyin.
是滴水观音
The Ministry of Justice
令郎的死因
[will investigate]
我刑部
[your son's]
异良人
death thoroughly.
一定会追查到底
What's the point...
追查什么
Liang.
老梁
Sorry for that.
多多担待
[Sorry.]
抱歉 抱歉
Farewell, Lord Liang.
梁大人慢走
Still on it?
还查吗
Ximing Temple's a royal monastery,
西明寺是敕建皇家寺院
where influential officials
全襄安有头有脸的
and nobles from
官宦贵人
all over Xiang'an come to pray.
都会来此上香
Gotta figure out
出了这种事
what happened.
自然得有个交代
Right.
对对对
Mrs. Liang's outburst has really
让梁大夫人那么一闹啊
thrown me off balance.
脑袋乱了
Investigate and
速速查案
conclude ASAP.
速速结案
Lu Chuichui.
陆垂垂
Yes, Sir.
到
Go.
去去去
Get those files
把已经查明的资料
back to the Ministry.
送回刑部归档
I heard the abbot of Ximing Temple
我听说西明寺的住持啊
has quite a collection of fine tea.
藏了不少好茶
Let's go
走
and have a taste.
我们去蹭口茶喝
Tea?
他还喝茶
Now? Seriously?
还好意思喝茶
Wu Taiming,
吴泰明
no peace,
无太平
just power abuse.
就知道作威作福
What a jerk.
什么东西
Yan.
六娘
You've been inspecting the corpse for long enough.
你都看了半天尸首了
You should come with me
等你看完
once you're done with it.
你跟我一起走啊
Even that
这吴泰明
wicked Wu is enjoying tea,
他都知道喝茶享福
we deserve better. Let's hit up
那我们也不能亏待自己
Furong Theater for some new drama
我带你去芙蓉园听新戏
and tasty brew.
喝好茶
You can go ahead.
垂垂你先回去吧
I'm gonna head to the pit
我还想再去尸坑
for another gander.
仔细看看
Go.
去吧
Okay.
好吧
Bye.
走了
[A toxic plant Guanyin?]
滴水观音
It seems you
看来你还是
haven't taken my words to heart.
没有记清我的话
I wouldn't dare.
六娘怎敢
Why are you here instead of
不在沈府好好待着
staying at home?
跑这儿来做什么
Though I'm married to you,
六娘虽然嫁进沈家
still a clerk at the Ministry.
但仍是刑部书吏
How could I not come when
此处发生了命案
there's a murder case?
怎能不来
You're just
你不过是一个
an unranked clerk.
刑部没有品阶的书吏
How come you're taking on
怎么还肩负起了
the duties of a coroner?
仵作之责
But it takes you,
我也没有听说过
chief of the IG,
内卫府大阁领
to put out fires
需要亲自灭火
[all night,]
为此整夜奔劳
missing his big day?
不惜错过良辰吉时
Boss.
大阁领
I checked it out.
刚问了异良人查探结果
Not much blood,
坑里的血量很少
just goo.
大多都是尸液
Liang and Kuang
梁邝二人
were probably
应该是血干得
moved here
差不多之后
dry.
才被运到了这里
No cart tracks nearby,
但这附近没有什么车辙
but plenty of footprints.
倒是有不少的脚印
With all these pilgrims,
这里香客无数
including Prince Ying,
连英王殿下都是常客
footprints aren’t gonna help much.
看脚印能看出什么
The shovel marks in the pit?
坑里的铲痕呢
Any idea when?
能看出什么时日的吗
Few days back,
应当是有些时日
the coroner says he can't be sure.
但仵作说不好判断时间
April 15th.
四月十五
How do you know?
你知道
The pit's sides are thin at the bottom,
土坑边沿下薄上厚
[thick at the top.]
落点尖边缘圆
Sharp points, round edges.
凶手亦或者是帮凶
The guy
用的是
used a regular shovel.
随处可见的圆头锹
Soil's loose around,
坑下泥土
but packed in the middle
边缘松散中心重
and bottom.
坑底泥土凝紧
Looks like it was dug after rain.
当是雨后土壤的表现
[Today is May 8th.]
今日是五月初八
Last rain
上一次下雨
was April 15th.
便是四月十五
Here you are.
给
I grabbed this candied fruit
我早上出来的时候
on my way out this morning.
顺手从屋里拿的
I'll ask the butler
我回去便要问问老管家
which shop it's from.
是哪家铺子买的蜜饯
So sweet.
这么甜
Take it.
给
Soil's tricky,
泥土变数多
your clues might be off.
你的发现未必可靠
See this mark,
你看这儿
three feet eight inches up?
大约离地三尺八寸
It's mud
有一道土痕
splatter.
是泥水飞溅而致
Temple's got yellow bamboo,
西明寺内竹乃是黄槽竹
which can grow
雨后一日
one to two inches a day after rain.
可长一寸至两寸
The mark points directly to the pit
溅痕直对尸坑
and is thick at bottom, thin at top.
痕迹下厚上薄
Definitely from that day.
是当日所造成的无疑啊
Chen Wen taught you all this?
陈瘟还教过你这些
Darling, I'm very
为夫对夫人
concerned about you.
可是非常上心
I've done my research.
仔细调查过一番
My master said,
我师父说过
catching and
凶手抓获
grilling criminals
下狱审理
is our job.
是刑部之责
So it's the duty of every official
所以想尽一切办法破案
in the Ministry to do whatever
是任何一个刑部人员的
it takes to crack a case.
职责所在
You're just
你不过是一个
an unranked clerk,
没有品阶的书吏
not your place to
刑部之责
worry about cracking cases.
怎么样也轮不到你头上
-I... -Just got married yesterday.
我 昨日刚刚新婚
Come back with me
今日便随我回沈府
and learn your duties as a wife.
好好学学新妇之责
You blew off our wedding night,
大阁领府草率迎亲
now everyone in Xiang'an
现在全襄安都知道
knows you're not interested in me,
大阁领不喜六娘
and frankly,
而偏巧
I'm not
我六娘呢
interested in you, either.
也不是很稀罕你大阁领
So from now on,
所以从今往后
let's just go our
我们各做各的
separate ways.
互不干扰
My duties are none
大阁领也不必劳心
of your concern.
我担哪个责
Seems I have to
看来今日
take this matter into my own hands
本阁领非得劳这个心
today.
不可了
Shen Du.
沈渡
Let go.
你放手
Put me down!
你放我下来
Shen Du. Shen Du.
沈渡 沈渡
What
你干吗
do you want?
你要干吗
The tea here really hits the spot.
还得是西明寺
Our office tea is nowhere
衙门里哪能喝到
near this good.
那么好的茶
So unlucky.
为夫不幸
I got a wife
娶了一个
who's all about her job.
一心为公务的夫人
Gotta sweeten her up at home.
只能带回府温存了
Put me down!
你快放我下来
Nice view.
风景不错
[What do you want?]
沈渡你要干吗
Put me down!
你快放我下来
Be a good girl,
夫人还是听话些
or I'll
要不然
kiss you right here.
当众和你恩爱了
The...
那
Yan... Yan Xing?
那谁谁谁 颜幸
And the...
和马上另一个是
Chief Shen.
沈大阁领
I heard The White Death
不是说白无常娶亲当日
[held a knife to]
就拿刀架在
his wife's throat on their big day.
沈夫人的脖颈上威胁吗
But looks like it's all just gossip.
这么看来都是谣传啊
Now,
如今
you're the
你已是
Mrs. Shen in everyone's eyes.
众人眼中的沈夫人
Once you're in,
既已入局
there's no turning
便再无全身而退的
back.
选择了
Putting on a show
沐猴而冠
like a clown,
大阁领演这一出
trying to earn a reputation
难不成是想落个
as a good husband?
良夫贤婿的风评
Since we're newlyweds,
你我新婚燕尔
it's only natural to be intimate.
自当比翼连枝
Today,
今日
I'll make you and
我一定让你
whoever is behind you happy.
还有你背后的人满意
IG's got a lot going on,
内卫府日理万机
sure you have
大阁领想必
a lot to handle
还有很多事情
for the Great
要替太皇太后
Grandmother.
处理和分忧
I'll just be
带着我
in the way.
怕是不方便吧
Are you dead or hurt?
夫人是死了还是残了
[Boss.]
大阁领
If not,
既然没死没残
what's the big deal?
有什么不方便的
A message from the palace.
宫中来函
[Wrap the case up quickly,]
速结西明寺梁府命案
[protect Liang Chenyu.]
保梁家二房梁尘昱
[No mistakes allowed.]
不得有误
Gotta go somewhere.
得去个地方了
Where?
去哪儿
Liang Mansion.
丰乐坊梁府
[What's going on?]
什么情况
[He's slacking,]
他不查案
[but I gotta keep digging.]
我还得查呢
[Can't just tag along like this.]
这么跟着他不是办法
Your Excellency. Young Master's
大阁领
waiting for you in the study.
我家三郎君在书房等你
Call me "darling",
不喊夫君
or I'll make you
出了梁府
regret it outside the Liang's.
舌头就别要了
Darling.
夫君
Yes?
说吧
Our jobs are different.
我跟你官属毕竟不同
You gotta meet Mr. Liang,
你有事要去找二房家主
I'll just be in the way.
我跟着也不是很方便
So
不如
I'll just wait outside.
我在外面等你吧
I just want a stroll.
我就是想出去走走
Fine.
好
Jing Lin.
景林
Stay with her.
跟着她
Yes.
是
This way, please.
大阁领 这边请
I've been up all night,
我熬了一宿没睡
gotta take a nap here.
我现在要在这儿睡一下
Watch my back over there.
你去那边替我守着
Fine.
行吧
If a guard like you
既然你们内卫
can stare at me, the wife
连大阁领夫人睡觉
of the chief when sleeping,
都能直视
I aren’t gonna be shy about it.
那我有什么好扭捏的呢
Whatever.
你自个儿守着吧
Mrs. Shen?
沈夫人
What are you doing here?
你怎么在这儿
Here, have this,
这个给你
it's really sweet.
可甜了
I heard the Liang's built
听说梁府分家之后
a wall after splitting.
砌了面墙
And the trees around here
我看这附近的树
seem to have been moved recently.
也像是后挪过来的
In our culture,
按理来说
pear, mulberry, and locust trees
这梨树 桑树和槐树
are considered unlucky.
都不算是吉利之选
Second Madame
是二夫人犯疯病的时候
had them moved when she was in madness.
让人挪的
Separation.
分离
Something's fishy.
指桑骂槐 心中有鬼
There is a deep grudge between the two brothers.
这两家兄弟积怨甚深啊
The word is that
难不成
Second Madam's son,
真如坊间传的那样
Liang Chenman,
二夫人之子梁尘曼
got poisoned by a toxic plant Guanyin
当年中了滴水观音之毒
by Madam Liang...
是被叔伯家的大房给
Don't say that.
这话可不敢说
But
不过
Second Madame
二夫人是
went crazy after her husband died.
自二郎君死后疯的
Since then,
自那之后
the door
大房跟二房
connecting them
墙上的那扇通门
has never been opened again.
就再也没有开过
My lady.
夫人
What are you...
夫人这是
Ducking The...
躲白
Ducking my husband.
我躲我夫君呢
Well.
那个
Since the wedding,
自我昨日嫁入之后吧
he's
我夫君
glued to me.
就一刻都不能离开我
Move a few feet,
我走一步他都得
he's got his guys on me.
派手下跟着我才行
I really need some air.
我实在是想喘口气
The Cold...
白
The chief's so clingy?
大阁领这么粘人的吗
I see.
原是如此
I was wondering.
奴婢还想呢
Mr. Shen visits often,
大阁领虽常来
but this is the first time
可却是第一次
he's brought a lady.
将女眷带入府中呢
He's been
我夫君
quite close with the Liang family?
竟与梁府走动甚密
He's quite close with
大阁领与我家三郎君
Young Master,
关系甚好
and often brings flowers
平常总带一些
or herbs
花草药材的
to Second Madame.
给梁二夫人
[Something's up again.]
二夫人的院子又出事了
[Hurry.]
快走啊
It's Second Madame.
是二夫人的院子
Her Highness has urged
太皇太后有谕
timely completion of
兵弩的改良图纸
the crossbow designs,
按期完成
no delays.
不得有误
But now,
可眼下
how can I focus on that?
我哪有心思绘制啊
IG's handling your
你哥梁尘重命案一事
brother's case,
是我内卫府查办的
so don't worry about that.
你大可放心
But...
这
Your family's known for
你家世代效力于工部
making top-notch crossbows.
精于弓弩机械
Your grandpa designed
我朝大部分兵弩装备
the most of our military gear,
都是由你祖父设计
which made us strong on the battlefield.
才能在沙场立威
Now, you're the
传到你这一代
only one who can
只有你一个人
keep that up.
能委此重任
The Empress Dowager values you.
太皇太后素来惜才
You should focus on getting
你只管专心完成
those designs done.
交代给你的事
Just like before,
和之前一样
whenever my father started drawing,
家父一提笔绘制
and your dad would just up and leave.
令尊就会马上转身离开
My dad never forgot
家父在临终前
what happened that year
一直也忘不了
even until his last breath.
那年的那件事
Shen Bingzhu confessed his guilt
罪臣沈秉烛
and deserves punishment.
其罪当诛
Forget about it.
不必再提了
[Rest assured.]
你放心
I won't make the same
我不会重蹈
mistakes he did.
那个人的覆辙
[Chenman.]
曼儿
The toxic plant?
滴水观音
Don't touch him.
别动我的曼儿
Chenman.
曼儿
Help!
救命
She's there.
大阁领 在那儿
Help me.
救我
[Shen Du.]
沈渡
[You're so mean!]
你好歹毒的心
[Couldn't get rid of me.]
赶不走我
[Trying to]
就想趁机
[drown me now?]
让我淹死在这儿
Help!
救命啊
Here.
来
Clean it up.
擦干净了
Take the lady to get cleaned up
快送大阁领夫人
and changed.
去沐浴更衣
[Sorry for any trouble today.]
今日之事多有得罪
Please forgive us.
还望大阁领和夫人见谅
[It's okay.]
无妨
Just tell your Young Master
转告你家三郎
to focus on his thing.
安心做他的事
[Yes.]
是
Let's go.
告辞了
[Who'd have guessed]
要不是亲眼所见
The White Death,
谁能想到
[who makes]
让世人
[everyone tremble, would be]
闻风丧胆的白无常
[such a considerate husband.]
竟是个体贴的夫君
[Tough exterior,]
对外无情郎
[has caring interior.]
实则多情种
What did you say
你跟那些侍女
to those maids?
都说什么了
Just helping you out,
配合你演戏
a loving husband, right?
做好夫君啊
In big families like this,
像这种大家门庭的丫鬟
maids love spreading gossip.
散布谣言是最为有效的
Why save me?
为何要救我
If I drowned,
我要是落水死了
it's done and
便是意外身故
you would get rid of me.
你也不用再想办法
Easy peasy,
赶我走了
right?
不是一举两得
You're still
留着你
useful to me.
我还有用
I got
老奴
your stuff ready,
已将夫人随身东西
[my lady.]
安顿好
You can sleep here tonight.
今夜您就在此就寝
The monk said
大师不是说
main chamber's bad for newlyweds,
主房不宜做新房
which may bring bad luck.
会容易引来血光之灾
The curse is dispelled,
大师已经破解了
you can relax and stay here.
您就放心地在这儿住吧
I think
我觉得
the west wing's got better vibes
西厢房的风水比较好
for me.
旺我
I'll head back there.
我还是回去住吧
[Stop.]
站住
You have no other options.
你没得选
But you can get out of here
想死的话
if you have a death wish.
你也可以离开沈府
Fine.
住就住
I'll stay.
谁怕谁
Let's see who
血光之灾
gets hurt in this "curse" thing.
还不一定谁见血呢
My lady.
夫人
You should wait for the chief.
郎君还没动筷呢
So what?
那怎么了
I'm hungry.
夫人我饿了
It was the Second Madame
今天害我落水的
who made me fall into the water.
就是梁府二夫人
Her son died
当年他的儿子
from that
因为中了
poison plant years ago,
滴水观音之毒而死
but she loved it
但她却把那盆毒物
like a kid,
当作自己的孩子
called it "Chenman".
还唤作曼儿
Now Liang Chenzhong's
如今这个大房梁尘重
poisoned by it too.
也中了滴水观音之毒
Crazy coincidence, huh?
怎么会这么巧
No talking while eating.
食不言
I'm done eating.
我吃好了
You think the young master's
你是不是也觉得
getting back at
梁尘重的死
Liang Chenzhong for revenge?
是梁家二房在报复
Boss.
大阁领
Deliver it.
送走
Yes.
是
Why the rush?
走这么急啊
He should stay for dinner.
也不吃完饭再走
You're talking too much.
话多
I eat, drink, talk,
你管人吃饭喝水
and blink as I please.
你还管人说话眨眼不成
Remember,
记住了
in Shen Mansion,
在沈府
you should pretend you're blind and deaf.
你最好选择做个瞎子
It's safer.
再做个聋子
Liang's case's
梁尘重一案
been handed over to IG.
已交由内卫府
It's our Ministry's case.
案子是我们刑部的
You're sharp, aren't you?
夫人不是很聪慧吗
Can't you figure out
太皇太后将案子
why the Empress Dowager
从刑部迁出
took the case
交由内卫府
away from you
其中用意
and gave it to us?
夫人不明白吗
She wanna sweep it under the rug?
太皇太后是想息事宁人
Liang's big in the Ministry of Works.
只因梁家是工部重臣
They make almost all
当朝的弓弩图绘制
the crossbow designs.
皆出于梁家之手
With Liang Chenman
二房梁尘曼意外暴毙
and Chenzhong gone,
梁尘重又突然死了
if their young master gets
如果再因家族私仇
dragged into family feuds,
牵扯到三郎君
who's gonna keep
势必会影响
the skills alive?
梁家技术的传承
You're not as slow as I thought.
还不算笨到底
The young master can't be put into prison,
梁家二房不能下狱
unless...
除非
you dare defy Empress Dowager.
你想顶撞太皇太后
Or is this
还是说
Zhang Xingwei's order?
这是张行微的意思
I don't work for Zhang.
我不是张相的人
You left that scroll on purpose,
你把卷筒留在房中
just to see what I'd do, huh?
是故意在试探我
Smart move,
你得感谢你的聪明
or you'd
要不然
be dead by now.
你现在已经人头落地了
I knew it was
其实根本不用打开
bow designs
我也能猜到
without even looking.
里面就是弓弩图
What are you laughing at?
笑什么
At you.
我在笑你
As the chief of the IG,
堂堂内卫府大阁领
you just jumped
未经核查
to the conclusion.
就认定凶手是梁家二房
But who knows?
但事实未必如此
She may hate Liang Chenzhong,
梁家二房与梁尘重有仇
but the murderer
可凶手
only slashed the courtesan's
却只是把歌伎的脸
face brutally.
划得刀刀见骨
I told you,
我说过
this case is none of your business.
这事不用你查
What if I insist?
若我非要查呢
Shut up and live,
要么做个活人噤声
or open
要么变成
your mouth and die.
不会说话的死人
Your Excellency.
大阁领
Let's make a bet.
不如我们赌一把
You think I won't kill you?
你是真不怕我会杀了你
I don't wanna die.
我当然怕
But you said
但你也说过
I'm still useful.
留着我还有用
You scared
怎么
you can't beat me in this bet?
大阁领是怕跟我赌输了
What's the bet?
怎么赌
I'll look into it.
让我查
If it's
若凶手
really Liang Chenyu,
真是梁家三郎梁尘昱
you got me.
就算你赢
I'll ask for a divorce,
到时我自请休妻
and you can do
我的性命
whatever you want with me.
也随大阁领处置
You're really
你还真是嫌
asking for trouble, aren't you?
自己命太长啊
If I crack this case,
但若是我查到凶手
we'll split up
三月之后
in three months.
你我和离
Neither of us wanted
这婚不只你不想娶
this marriage.
我也不想嫁
So let's just
你我无冤无仇
call it quits and
不求百年好合
part on good terms.
只求好聚好散
Fine.
好
[I'm gotta make it through]
无论如何
[the next three months.]
也要扛过三个月
[After the exams,]
到时女官考核完
[my transfer]
出使外调的事
[should be set in stone.]
也该尘埃落定了
I shouldn't live
我住这主屋
in the main chamber, huh?
不太好吧
Do as I say.
让你住就住
Our marriage is blessed by
我们是太皇太后
the Empress Dowager.
御赐的婚姻
We must appear
在任何人看来
loving and
都应该恩爱有加
inseparable.
如胶似漆
Mess up, and you're...
如果你做不到的话
I'm dead.
那就又要掉脑袋呗
Alright, I got it.
行了 我知道了
Gotta say,
你别说啊
I feel
我觉得
quite at home in this room.
我跟这个主屋还挺合的
Since I'm the wife now,
那既然如此
make sure I get
那当家主母的待遇
all the perks that come with it.
可都得跟上啊
Make it a convincing show.
做戏做全套嘛
I'm sleeping here.
那我睡这儿
Where's your spot?
你睡哪儿
Like you said, huh?
不是你说的吗
Per
全
Perks.
全套
As newlyweds,
新婚燕尔
we gotta stick together like glue
如胶似漆
and sleep in the same bed.
只能同床共枕了
With your clothes on?
你穿着外衣上我的床
This is how I roll at home.
我在家里一向如此
If you're not used to it,
夫君若是不习惯的话
deal with it.
那就适应一下吧
You're right.
夫人说得对
I suppose I should.
的确应该适应一下
You're squishing my hair!
你压我头发了
Gotta say,
你别说啊
the candied fruits are really delicious.
这沈府的蜜饯真好吃
Can't get enough.
怎么吃都吃不够
So yummy.
不错不错
Wanna try one?
你来一个吗
You...
你
Zhong.
忠叔
Get it
换了
Changed!
全换了
It's too bright.
灯这么亮
Blow it out, will ya?
能不能熄了
No.
不能
Can't sleep with it on.
那这么亮我怎么睡啊
You could stay awake.
你可以不睡
[Chi.]
小池池
[How's life treating you in Jiangnan?]
你在江南近来可好
[I just cracked a case.]
最近我破获了
[A wife was killed by her husband.]
一起杀妻案
[It's not suicide.]
死者不是自杀
[Let me walk you through]
我来给你还原一下
[the scene.]
当时的情景
Yuanniang.
芫娘
[After strangling Wang Yuanniang,]
你勒死了王芫娘后
[you looped the rope round her neck,]
套住尸身的颈部
[dragged her under the beam,]
拖到房梁处
[hooked the other end]
又将麻绳的另一头
[up there,]
挂上房梁
[and hoisted her up.]
用力将她吊起
[All that left]
而这一切
marks on the beam,
都在梁上留下了痕迹
[which is why]
所以
[her neck's got]
她的脖子上出现了
[two kinds of marks:]
两道不同的勒痕
[black ones down,]
黑色向后
[and brown ones up top.]
褐色向上
Plus, you got
你的手上
rope burns on your hands.
还有麻绳勒出的伤痕
She was strangled by you to death.
她就是被你勒死的
Ms. Yan.
颜书吏
Ms. She's already copped to
佘娘子已经认了
[helping Cheng Xian]
她协助程嫌
[kill his wife.]
杀妻一事
Yuanniang did the stitching, right?
这件小衫是芫娘绣的吧
The coroner checked
经仵作查验
and found out
王芫娘
she was carrying a two-month-old baby.
已经有了两个月的身孕
You're lying.
你在诱骗我
So what if she was
她就算是怀了身孕
pregnant?
那又如何
You killed her 'cause you couldn't
你为入赘不甘
handle being married into her family.
愤而谋杀王芫娘
But you didn't know
可你却不知道
she loved you so much
她对你痴心一片
she wanted the baby
早就打算孩子出生后
to take your name.
便随你姓氏
The shirt has your surname
这小衫上绣的
on it.
便是程姓
You blame her family for
你处处怪王芫娘的母家
oppressing you,
欺压于你
but you know the real story.
可事实如何你最清楚
Yuanniang.
芫娘
I'm so sorry.
我对不起你啊 芫娘
[There's this weird]
只是死者身上
[little pin hole on the body,]
还有一个针眼伤口
[and the coroner]
很是奇怪
[doesn't know what caused it yet.]
仵作暂时也没验出由来
[I've been through]
最近在我身上
[many changes lately.]
发生了不少变故
It's dawn.
五更